<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The order of my Lord Mayor, the aldermen, and the sheriffes for their meetings and wearing of their apparrell thoroughout the whole yeare.</title>
            <author>City of London (England).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16730.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23152624</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23152624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26304</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26304)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1799:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The order of my Lord Mayor, the aldermen, and the sheriffes for their meetings and wearing of their apparrell thoroughout the whole yeare.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Young, printer to the hon. city of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Corporation of London --  Rules and practice.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26304:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26304:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>arms</figDesc>
               </figure> THE ORDER OF MY LORD MAYOR, The Aldermen, and the SHERIFFES, <hi>For their meetings and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of their Apparrell <hi>tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout the whole</hi> yeare.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>R. Young,</hi> Printer to the Hon: City of London. 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:26304:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26304:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>VPon Midſomer day, for the election of the Sheriffes of London &amp;c. 1</item>
               <item>On Bartholomew Euen for the Faire in Smithfield. 4</item>
               <item>On Bartholomew day for wreſtling. 5</item>
               <item>For our Lady day in Southwarke. 6</item>
               <item>For the ſwearing of the Sheriffes vpon Michaelmaſſe Euen. 7</item>
               <item>Vpon Michaelmaſſe day, for the election of my Lord Mayor. 8</item>
               <item>For the preſenting of my Lord Elect to the Lord Chancellor. 12</item>
               <item>The morrow after Michaelmaſſe day, for the Sheriffes going to Weſtminſter. ibid.</item>
               <item>The order for Simon and Iudes day. 15</item>
               <item>On the morrow after Simon and Iudes day, for my Lords going to take his oath at Weſtminſter. 17</item>
               <item>For going to Pauls on All-Saints day, Chriſtmaſſe day, Twelfth day, and Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe day. 20</item>
               <item>Vpon S. Thomas day. 21</item>
               <item>For the Chriſmaſſe Holydayes. ibid.</item>
               <item>Vpon Innocents day. ibid.</item>
               <item>For Munday after Twelfth day. 22</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26304:3"/>
               <item>For Good Friday. ibid.</item>
               <item>For Munday &amp; Tueſday in Eaſter week. 23</item>
               <item>For Wedneſday in Eaſter week. ibid.</item>
               <item>For Low Sunday. 24</item>
               <item>For Whitſunday. ibid.</item>
               <item>For Munday and Tueſday in Whitſon weeke. ibid.</item>
               <item>For the Lord Mayors Knighthood. 25</item>
               <item>For going to Pauls the firſt Sunday of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Tearme. ibid.</item>
               <item>For election of Knights and Burgeſſes of the Parliament. 26</item>
               <item>For the Lords of the Councell comming downe for Subſidies. 27</item>
               <item>For the election of Maſter Chamberlain and Bridge Maſters, if any of them depart within the yeare. ibid.</item>
               <item>For the Coronation of a King. 28</item>
               <item>The vſe of my Lords Cloake. ibid.</item>
               <item>For the firſt day of euery Quarter Seſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 29</item>
               <item>For the buriall of Aldermen. 30</item>
               <item>For the nomination of an Alderman. ib.</item>
               <item>For the Orphanes Court. 31</item>
               <item>At the election of Gouernors for Chriſts Hoſpitall. ibid.</item>
               <item>Courts of Aldermen. 32</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26304:3"/>
            <head>Vpon Midſommer day, for the election of the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes of London. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lo: Mayor &amp; the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, with the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, meet at the Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall at eight of the clocke in the morning, apparelled in their Violet Gownes lined, and their Cloakes of Scarlet lined, without their Horſes.</p>
            <p>And when they haue beene to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Councell Chamber a certaine time, concerning the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of certaine perſons to bee Elected, my Lord and the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men come out, and put on their Cloakes in the Orphanes Court,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26304:4"/> and then goe downe in order to the Huſtings Court, and there beeing ſet, maſter Recorder ſtandeth vp, and maketh his obeyſance: firſt to my Lord, and then vnto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and declareth vnto them, wherefore they are aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhewing vnto them that it is for the election of one of the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes of London, and the Sheriffe of Middleſexe, for the yeare next enſuing, and the confirmation of the other Sheriffe, nominated by my Lord Maior, according to his prerogatiue: and alſo for maſter Chamberlaine, and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
            <p>But my Lord and the Aldermen goe vp to my Lords Court, and there remaine vntill the Sheriffe be named and choſen, the door ſhut to them.</p>
            <p>Then M. Sheriffs, M. Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine, maſter common Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26304:4"/> maſter Towne-Clearke, and the Counſellors of the Citie, and other Officers, remaine ſtill in the Huſtings Court, to take and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Name of him that ſhall ſeeme by their iudgements, freely and with one conſent, to bee nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and elected, and iuſtly tryed out, not onely by voyce, but alſo by hands, to be ſheriffe for the yeare following.</p>
            <p>Then the commons go to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of maſter Chamberlayne, the two Bridge-maſters, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors of the Citie, and Bridge-houſe accounts, and the Suruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Beere and Ale, according to the accuſtomed manner.</p>
            <p>That done, the Sheriffes, ma. Chamberlaine, ma. Common Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, M. Town-Clerk, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors of the City, the two Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries, and the Wardens of the head companies, maſt. Common
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26304:5"/> Cryer going before them with his Mace, carry vp the report to my Lord and the Aldermen of their ſaid election.</p>
            <p>Which report receiued, my Lord and the Aldermen come downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the Huſtings Court, and there being ſet in order and placed, maſter Recorder ſtandeth vp as he did before, and maketh rehearſal of the names of thoſe whom they haue nominated &amp; choſen, aſking them whether it bee their free election, yea or no. And they grant yea, yea. Then maſt. Recorder giueth them thankes, and ſo they ariſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part home.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>On Bartholmew Euen for the Faire in Smithfield.</head>
               <p>THe Aldermen meete my Lord and the Sheriffs at the Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall Chappell at two of the clocke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26304:5"/> after dinner, in their violet Gowns lined, and their horſes, without cloakes, and there heare Euening Prayer: which being done, they take their horſes and ride to New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and ſo forth of the gate, ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring into the cloth Fayre, and there make a proclamation: the procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation being made, they ride tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the cloth Faire, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne backe againe thorough the Churchyard of great S. Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomews to Alderſgate, and ſo ride home againe to the Lord Mayors houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>On Bartholomew day for wreſtling.</head>
               <p>SO many Aldermen as doe dine with my L. Mayor &amp; the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes be apparrelled in their ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gownes lined, and after dinner their Horſes hee brought to them where they dine and thoſe Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which dine with the ſheriffs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26304:6"/> ride with them to my Lords houſe to accompany him to the wreſtling. Then when the wreſtling is done, they take their horſes &amp; ride backe againe through the Fayre, and ſo in at Alderſgate, and ſo home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the ſaide Lord Mayors houſe.</p>
               <p>The next day, if it be not Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, for the ſhooting, as vpon Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew day: but if it bee Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, the monday following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For our Lady day in Southwarke.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Embroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered cap, pearle ſword, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Eſſes without whood.</note>My Lord Mayor and the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, ride to S. Magnus Church in thoſe ſcarlet Gownes lyned, without their Cloakes, after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at ii. of the clocke, and there the Aldermen meete my Lord, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Euening Prayer, they ride thorough the Fayre, till they come vnto Saint Georges Church, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26304:6"/> further to Newington Bridge, or to S. Thomas of Waterings, to the ſtones that point out the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the City (if it bee ſo their pleaſures) and they returne backe againe, vnto the Bridge-houſe, and haue a banquet there, and then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Bridge, and there the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen take their leaue of my Lo. and depart the next way, euery one to his houſe. And after all is done, and my Lord brought home, my L. Maiors Officers haue a Supper made them by the Bridgemaſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſwearing of the Sheriffes vpon Michaelmas euen.</head>
               <p>What day ſoeuer it falleth, ſo many of the Aldermen as be bidden to dinner to either of the Sheriffs come thither to Breakefaſt, or elſe to drinke, at eight of the clocke in the Morning, in theyr violet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26304:7"/> Gownes furred, with their violet Cloakes furred, brought with them, without horſes: and if the Sheriffe bee an Alderman, then they muſt put on their cloakes, and the ſheriffe likewiſe his cloake, and ſo goe to the Guild-hall betweene two of the gray cloakes: and if the Sheriffe be no Alderman, then to come betweene two of the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men without cloakes, and the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe his Liuery gowne &amp; his hood. And after when he is ſworne, then to put on his violet Gowne and Cloake, and his chaine theron: and the Aldermen muſt bring him home to his place, with their cloakes, to Dinner, and ſo after Dinner take their pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon Michaelmas day, for the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Lo: Mayor.</head>
               <p>All the Aldermen meet my Lord
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26304:7"/> and the Sheriffes at eight of the clocke in the morning at Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, in their ſcarlet Gownes and their cloakes furred, and their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and after they haue been a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time together in the counſell Chamber, they come forth into the Orphanes Court, and put on their Cloakes, and ſo goe in order to the Chappell, there hearing Seruice and Sermon, and my Lord with certain Aldermen, receiue the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p>And then after the Communion ended, and haue offered, returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the Councell Chamber, and pauſing a while, returne to the place where the Huſtings is kept: and being ſet in order, maſter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder ariſeth vp, and maketh his obeyſance firſt to my Lord, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Commons, and declareth vnto them that they of old cuſtome know that the cauſe of their aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26304:8"/> and meeting together, is for the election of the Lord Maior for the yeare enſuing: Declaring vnto them diuers Graunts from the Kings Progenitors, for this their Election from time to time. That done, my Lord and the Aldermen goe vp into my Lords Court, and there tarrie (the doore being ſhutte to them) till the election be brought to them. Then ſtandeth vp maſter Common Sergeant (the Sheriffs ſtanding on either ſide of him) and by the Sheriffes, M. Chamberlain M. Towne-clearke, the two Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condaries, and the councellors of the citie, in the ſaid Huſtings court before the Commons. And hee the ſaid common Sergeant, maketh a ſhort rehearſal of that M. Recorder had ſpoken to them before, ſaying: There reſteth no more for him to ſay but to put them in remembrance, in what order and ſort they ſhould vſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26304:8"/> themſelues in their election, that is, how they muſt nominate and chuſe two, of the which two my Lord and the Aldermen muſt confirme one: which two being nominated, elected and choſen, maſter Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sergeant, the Sheriffes, with the reſt before named, &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the head Wardens of the chiefe Companies goe vp to my Lord and the Aldermen, and there preſent the names of thoſe two which the Commons haue nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in their election.</p>
               <p>Then the Lord Mayor and the Aldermen proceede by ſcrutinie to elect one of thoſe two perſons, which the ſaid Commons had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nominated. Then commeth downe my Lord againe to the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings Court, and hee whom they haue choſen, on his left hand, and ſo my Lord and the Aldermen ſit downe againe in order: but he who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26304:9"/> is choſen, ſitteth next vnto my Lord, on his left hand. Then ſtandeth maſter Recorder vp, and readeth vnto them the names of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom they haue nominated and choſen: of which my Lord and the Aldermen haue admitted one, whoſe name is <hi>N.</hi> aſking them whether it bee their free Election, yes or no: And the Commons an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Yea, yea. Then the Sword-bearer taketh off his Tippet, and hath it for his labour, and putteth on his Chaine, and the Maior new elected ſtandeth vpon the Huſtings Court, and giueth them thankes, &amp;c. That being done, the old May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or doth likewiſe giue them thanks &amp;c. Then they ariſe vp, and put off their cloakes, and my Lord Maior hath the Lord Elect riding with him to the eldeſt Sheriffes to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:26304:9"/>
               <head>For preſenting of my Lo. Elect to the L. Chancellor (or Keeper.)</head>
               <p>THen after dinner, my Lord E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect goeth to my Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, if hee be at home at his place,<note place="margin">Or Lord Keeper.</note> or neere vnto it, with fiue or ſixe of the Aldermen, and maſter Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with him, in their violet Gownes, eyther by foote or by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as the dwelling place of the Chancellour requireth. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hunt, with the extraordinary Officers, and thoſe that be at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, attend on him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The morrow after Michaelmaſſe day for the Sheriffes going to Weſtminſter.</head>
               <p>ALl the Aldermen muſt be at the two Sheriffes houſes in the morning at eight of the clocke, in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26304:10"/> their violet Gownes furred, and their Horſes, without Cloaks: but my Lord, maſter Recorder, and the two Sheriffes muſt bee in their ſcarlet Gownes furred, and their cloaks borne to Weſtminſter with them, and ſo ride to the Guild-hall, &amp; from thence to the Vinetree, and there taking Barge, land at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-bridge, and in the Hall put on their cloakes, and ſo goe vp to the Exchequer: and there the two new Sheriffes be preſented, &amp; the old ſworne to their account.</p>
               <p>Then they put off their cloaks, and taking Barge, land againe at the Vinetree, and there take horſe: and my Lord Mayor rideth to the eldeſt Sheriffes to dinner, maſter Recorder and the Sheriffs riding next my Lord, the two Sheriffes carrying two white rods in their hands, and their Hench men going after them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:26304:10"/>
               <head>For Simon and Iudes day.</head>
               <p>THe olde Mayor ſhall haue ſo many of the Aldermen as dine with him come to his place at viii. of the clock in the morning, in their violet Gownes furred, with their violet Cloaks furred, and Horſes, and the Sheriffes to fetch him to the Hall, and there tarrie in the Councell Chamber vntill the new Mayor commeth, and the reſt of the Aldermen come, with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of eyther of the Lords before them: and after they haue bin to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a certaine ſpace, come forth into the Orphanes Court, and put on their furred Cloaks, and goe to the Huſtings Court: and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet in order, the common Cryer maketh Proclamation, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euery man to keepe ſilence.</p>
               <p>Then maſter Towne-Clerke
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26304:11"/> giueth him his oath: and when he hath taken his oath, the old Lord ariſeth, and giueth the new Lord his place, the old Lord taking the new Lords place: and then maſter Chamberlaine deliuereth firſt to him the Scepter, next the Keyes of the common Seale, laſtly, the Seale of the office of the Maioral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, after, maſter Sword-bearer gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him the Sword. Then they ariſe and put off their cloakes and the old Lord rideth home with the new Lord to his place, and there leaueth him, and as many of the Aldermen as dine with him. And the old Lord, with the reſt of the Aldermen, ride to his place, the ſword borne before him, and ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner, the Aldermen depart home at their pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:26304:11"/>
               <head>On the morrow after Simon &amp; Iudes day, for my Lord going to take his Oath at Weſtminſter.</head>
               <p>ALl the Aldermen and the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes come to my new Lord at eight of the clocke in their ſcarlet Gownes furred,<note place="margin">A Veluet whood. Cap of Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> and their cloakes borne with them, and their horſes, and ſo ride to the Guild-hall, and the Batchellors and the Liuery of my Lords Company before him.</p>
               <p>But the olde Lord rideth from his owne place to the Hall alone, hauing no Officers to waite vpon him, but the common Hunt, as a Gentleman Vſher going, and thoſe officers that be at libertie, and the common Hunt his man,<note place="margin">A Veluet whood for both May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors.</note> (with his own men following him) and ſo tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth at the Hall.</p>
               <p>And after they be come all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26304:12"/> they take their horſes, &amp; ride to the Vinetree, and there take Barge to Weſtminſter bridge.</p>
               <p>And after they be landed, the Lord Mayor and the Aldermen put on their Cloaks within the Palace, and goe round about the Hall, making curteſie in the Hall, and ſo go vp to the Exchequer to be ſworn. Then after the oath taken in the Exchequer, they come down againe, and goe firſt to the Kings Bench, then to the common Place, and ſo put off their Cloaks, and go about the Kings Tombe in Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter Abbey, &amp; then take Barge againe: And being landed, rideth to the Guild-hall to dinner, and all the Companies of this City with him: and at their comming into the Hall, the new Lord Mayor, with two of the ancient Aldermen, maſter Recorder and the Sheriffs, goe vp to my Lords Table to bid
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26304:12"/> them welcome; and likewiſe all the other gueſts there, and from thence to the Lady Maioreſſe Table, and ſo come out to the Gentlewomens Table, and to the Iudges, and ſo from thence my ſaid new L. Mayor goeth into the Chamberlaines Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, where he dineth, and the olde Lord Maior at their firſt comming into the Hall, goeth vp to the high Table in the Huſtings, and there keepeth the State for that Feaſt. And after the Hall is almoſt ſerued of the ſecond, then the new Lord Mayor goeth with ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and thoſe Aldermen that dine with him, to bid the old Lord and all the gueſts in the Hall welcome. Then after dinner goeth to Pauls with all the Companies wayting before my Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:26304:13"/>
               <head>For going to Pauls or All-Saints day, Chriſtmaſſe day, Twelfth day, and Candlemaſſe day.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Veluet whood for both. All Saints day is the laſt day that the old Lord rideth with the new. Capp of Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note>ALl the Aldermen &amp; the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes come to my Lords place in their ſcarlet Gownes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and their cloaks and Horſes, and from thence ride to the Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, my Lords company and the Batchellers before him, and there heareth Euening Prayer: and when prayer is done, they ride to Pauls, and there both the new Lo: Mayor and the olde put on their cloakes, and goe vp to the Quite, and there heare the ſermon: which done, they goe about the Church, &amp; there put off their cloakes where they were put on. Then they take their Horſes again, and the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bring my L. home, &amp; then they haue ſpice bread and hypocraffe, and ſo take their leaue of my Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:26304:13"/>
               <head>Vpon S. Thomas day.</head>
               <p>THe Lord Mayor and euery Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman is to ſit in his Ward in his violet Gowne &amp; Cloak furred.<note place="margin">If it be not Sunday.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Chriſtmaſſe Holydaies.</head>
               <p>FOr Chriſtmaſſe Holydayes, vntill Twelfth day,<note place="margin">No Cloak</note> if my Lord and the Aldermen goe abroad to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny publicke meeting, they are to weare ſcarlet: but on the working dayes within the twelue dayes, if my Lord goe to the Guild-hall, Markets or Streets, they weare blacke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vpon Innocents day.</head>
               <p>VPon Innocents day the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen dyne at my Lords,<note place="margin">No State.</note> and the Sheriffes, in ſcarlet: but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26304:14"/> the Ladies weare blacke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Munday after Twefth day.</head>
               <p>MY Lord and the Aldermen meet at the Guild-hall at viii. of the clock in the morning, in their ſcarlet Gownes furred, and their Cloakes furred, without Horſe, to receiue of their Wards their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentures of the Wardmote In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and for the ſwearing of the Conſtables and Scauengers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Good Friday.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Blacke Sword.</note>MY Lord and the Aldermen meet at Paules Croſſe at one of the clocke to heare the Sermon, in their pewke Gownes, &amp; without their Chaines and Tippets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:26304:14"/>
               <head>For Monday and Tueſday in Eaſter Weeke.</head>
               <p>ALl the Aldermen and Sheriffs come vnto my Lords place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eight of the clocke to breake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt,<note place="margin">A Whood for my L.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Capp of Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> in their ſcarlet Gownes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and their Cloaks and Horſes: and after breake-faſt, take their Horſes, &amp; ride to the Spittle, and there put on their Cloakes, and ſo ſit down in order to heare the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: which done, ride homeward in order, til they come to the Pump within Biſhopſgate, and there ſo many of the Aldermen as doe dine with the Sheriffes, take their leaue of my Lord, and the reſt goe home with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Wedneſday in Eaſter Weeke.</head>
               <p>LIke as before on the other two dayes, ſaue that my Lord and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26304:15"/> the Aldermen muſt be in their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let gownes, and ſutable cloaks, but the Ladies in blacke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Low Sunday.</head>
               <p>ALl the Aldermen meet my Lo: and the Sheriffes at Paules Schoole in their ſcarlet Gownes furred, without their cloakes or horſe, to heare the Sermon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Whitſunday.</head>
               <p>FOr Whitſunday all the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men meet my Lord and the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes at the new Church-yard, in their ſcarlet Gownes fined, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cloakes, to heare the Sermon: which being ended, they depart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Munday and Tueſday in Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon weeke.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re be to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe.</note>ALl the Aldermen muſt meet my Lo: Mayor and the Sheriffs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26304:15"/> at Pauls in their ſcarlet Gowns, without Cloaks, to heare the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Lord Mayors Knighthood.</head>
               <p>ALl the Aldermen meet my Lo: eyther at the three Cranes (if the King be at Weſtminſter) or at S. Mary hill (if the King be at Greenwich) by ſeuen of the clocke in the morning, in their ſcarlet Gownes, and Cloaks borne with them: and after Morning Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they take Barge to the Kings place, where they attend till that ceremony be ended, and ſo go home with my Lord Mayor to dinner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Forgoing to Paules the firſt Sunday of euery Tearme.</head>
               <p>ALl the Aldermen meet my Lo: and the Sheriffs at Paules, in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26304:16"/> their ſcarlet Gownes, furted or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, without Cloakes or Horſe, as the time of the yeare requireth when the Tearme beginneth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For election of Knights and Burgeſſes of the Parliament.</head>
               <p>ALl the Aldermen meet my Lo: and the Sheriffs at Guildhall at nine of the clocke, in their violet Gownes and their Cloaks, furred or lyned, as the time of the yeare when they ſhalbe choſen, requireth, and ſitteth in the Huſlings Court while the Commons chuſe them. The order is, that they muſt chuſe maſter Recorder for one of their Knights, and one gray Cloake for the other, and two commoners for the Burgeſſes: which done, they depart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:26304:16"/>
               <head>For the Lords of the Councell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe for Subſidies.</head>
               <p>FOr the Lords and Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners comming downe to aſſeſſe the Subſidies, my L: Mayor and the Aldermen weare their blacke gownes as at other times, and the commiſſioners are to bee warned by maſter Sheriffes officers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the election of Maſter Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine and Bridge Maſters, if any of them depart within the yeare.</head>
               <p>MY Lord and the Aldermen ſit in the Huſtings court while they be choſen, in their violet gownes without their cloaks, and doe not remoue vntill the election be done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:26304:17"/>
               <head>For the Coronation of a King.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">My Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n a crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on veluet Gowne, Coller of Eſſes and Scepter. No cloak</note>ALl the Aldermen meet my Lo: and the Sheriffes at the three Cranes in the Vinetree, at the houre of their ſummons, in their ſcarlet gownes, and cloakes borne with them, lined or furred, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the time of the yeare, where taking Barge, they land at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, &amp; there they attend in the Checquer Chamber (being ſerued with wine and cakes) vntill they are called by the Heraulds: then they put on their cloaks.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The vſe of my Lords Cloake.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Beginning vpon Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas Euen.</note>FRom Michaelmaſſe to Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontide, violet furred: and from Whitſontide to Michaelmaſſe ſcarlet, lined.</p>
               <p>The Lord Mayor and thoſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26304:17"/> Knights that haue borne the office of Maioraltie, ought to haue their cloaks furred with gray Amis, and thoſe Aldermen that haue not been Mayors, are to haue their cloakes furred with Calabre.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe ſuch as haue beene Mayors, are to haue their cloakes lined with changeable Taffata, and the reſt are to haue them lined with greene Taffata.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the firſt day of euery Quarter Seſsions.</head>
               <p>THe firſt day of euery quarter ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the forenoone only, my Lord &amp; the Sheriffes weare their violet gownes and cloakes furred; but at Midſomer quarter ſeſſions, the firſt day they weare violet gownes and ſcarlet cloaks, and on the other dayes blacke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:26304:18"/>
               <head>For the buriall of Aldermen.</head>
               <p>THe Aldermen muſt be in their violet gownes, except ſuch as haue of their friends black gowns. When any Alderman dyeth, maſter Sword-bearer is to haue a blacke gowne, or xxxiii. s. iiii. d. in money: and if hee giueth my Lord a blacke gowne, maſter Sword-bearer is to haue another, or xl. s. in money the price thereof, and ſo carry the ſword in blacke before my Lord.</p>
               <p>Maſter Chamberlaine is not to weare his Tippet but when my L. Mayor or the Aldermen weare their ſcarlet or violet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>At the nomination of an Alderman.</head>
               <p>FOr the nomination of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman, my Lord weareth his blacke gowne and violet cloak, and both the ſheriffs black gowns.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:26304:18"/>
               <head>For the Orphanes Court.</head>
               <p>MY Lord and the Aldermen meet at the Guild-hal in their violet gownes without cloaks, but my L. Mayor muſt haue his cloak: This court the common Cryer warneth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>At the election of Gouernours at Chriſts Hoſpitall.</head>
               <p>FOr the election of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the ſeueral Hoſpitals, the L. Mayor and the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men weare black gownes.</p>
               <p>The foure Pleaders, the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine, Town-clerke, Common Sergeant, two Iudges of the Sheriffs Court, the Secondaries, Vnder Chamberlain and Bridge-maſters, are to attend my Lord at his houſe before his going abroad vpon all feſtiuall times, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:26304:19"/>
               <head>Courts of Aldermen.</head>
               <p>COurts of Aldermen in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, are kept at the Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall euery Tueſday &amp; Thurſday through the whole yeare, except holy-dayes, the moneth of Auguſt, vntill Bartholmew day be paſt, the week before Chriſtmaſſe, Shrone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tueſday, and the weeke before Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:26304:19"/>
            <head>The names of the ſeuerall Companies <hi>in their order.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Mercers.</item>
               <item>Grocers.</item>
               <item>Drapers.</item>
               <item>Fiſhmongers.</item>
               <item>Goldſmiths.</item>
               <item>Skinners.</item>
               <item>Merchantaylors.</item>
               <item>Haberdaſhers.</item>
               <item>Salters.</item>
               <item>Ironmongers.</item>
               <item>Vintners.</item>
               <item>Clothworkers.</item>
               <item>Dyers.</item>
               <item>Brewers.</item>
               <item>Leatherſellers,</item>
               <item>Pewterers.</item>
               <item>Cutlers.</item>
               <item>White-Bakers.</item>
               <item>Waxe Chandlers.</item>
               <item>Tallow Chandlers.</item>
               <item>Armourers.</item>
               <item>Girdlers.</item>
               <item>Butchers.</item>
               <item>Sadlers.</item>
               <item>Carpenters.</item>
               <item>Cordwayners.</item>
               <item>Barberſurgeons.</item>
               <item>Painterſtayners.</item>
               <item>Curriers.</item>
               <item>Maſons.</item>
               <item>Plummers.</item>
               <item>Inholders.</item>
               <item>Fownders.</item>
               <item>Poulters.</item>
               <item>Cookes.</item>
               <item>Coopers.</item>
               <item>Tylers &amp; Bricklayers</item>
               <item>Bowyers.</item>
               <item>Fletchers.</item>
               <item>Black Smiths.</item>
               <item>Ioyners.</item>
               <item>Weauers.</item>
               <item>Woolmen.</item>
               <item>Woodmongers.</item>
               <item>Scriueners.</item>
               <item>Fruterers.</item>
               <item>Plaiſterers.</item>
               <item>Browne Bakers.</item>
               <item>Stationers.</item>
               <item>Imbroyderers.</item>
               <item>Vpholders.</item>
               <item>Muſitions.</item>
               <item>Turners.</item>
               <item>Basketma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Glaſiers.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
